<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Niladri Shekhar Dutt</title>
    <link>https://niladridutt.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Niladri Shekhar Dutt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://niladridutt.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding deep learning requires rethinking generalization - A discussion</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2020/06/understanding-deep-learning-requires-rethinking-generalization-a-discussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2020/06/understanding-deep-learning-requires-rethinking-generalization-a-discussion/</guid>
      <description>Deep neural networks have been highly successful at a number of tasks; this paper takes a step back and looks at why such deep architectures have been successful. In deep neural networks more often than not, we have far more trainable parameters than the number of training examples and for some reason they seem to generalize very well despite violating the conventional rules of statistical learning. This paper seeks to understand generalization at a very fundamental level and tries to answer what causes a neural network to go beyond memorising labels and actually build intuitions about the underlying patterns in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Hacker’s Guide to Winning Hackathons</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2019/06/a-hackers-guide-to-winning-hackathons/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2019/06/a-hackers-guide-to-winning-hackathons/</guid>
      <description>Hackathons are exhilarating. Nothing can eclipse the sheer adrenaline pump of building something in 24–36 hours. I was a visiting student at UC Berkeley for the Spring’19 semester. Berkeley is really close to the Silicon Valley and that gave me an amazing opportunity to take part in and win these 3 amazing hackathons:
  LA Hacks ’19 hosted by UCLA
  San Francisco DeveloperWeek Hackathon ’19 (America’s largest challenge-driven hackathon)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a Data Scientist at NFTPort where I lead AI x blockchain services to build enhanced APIs for NFTs.
Previously, I have had the good fortune of working with Dr.Brandie Nonnecke at UC Berkeley at the intersection of machine learning and social network analysis. I have also spent time as a research intern at Nvidia and IIT Kharagpur.
If you&amp;rsquo;re starting your journey in machine learning, check this roadmap I maintain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>E-mail : niladrishekhardutt@gmail.com
GitHub : niladridutt
Twitter : @dutt_niladri
LinkedIn : niladridutt
Schedule a 30 min meeting with me</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/experience/</guid>
      <description>NFTPort
Data Scientist | Oct 2020 - Present
  I lead AI x blockchain services to build enhanced APIs for NFTs. Developed core functionalties like NFT search, duplicate detection, recommendation engine from scratch. Maintain core API design and RESTful practices in an API-first company.  
 Nvidia Corporation
Research Intern | Jan 2020 - Jun 2020
  Researched how regularity affects learning in GANs by studying modelling on synthetic data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
