<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Niladri Shekhar Dutt</title>
    <link>https://niladridutt.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Niladri Shekhar Dutt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://niladridutt.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding deep learning requires rethinking generalization - A discussion</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2020/06/understanding-deep-learning-requires-rethinking-generalization-a-discussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2020/06/understanding-deep-learning-requires-rethinking-generalization-a-discussion/</guid>
      <description>Deep neural networks have been highly successful at a number of tasks; this paper takes a step back and looks at why such deep architectures have been successful. In deep neural networks more often than not, we have far more trainable parameters than the number of training examples and for some reason they seem to generalize very well despite violating the conventional rules of statistical learning. This paper seeks to understand generalization at a very fundamental level and tries to answer what causes a neural network to go beyond memorising labels and actually build intuitions about the underlying patterns in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Hacker’s Guide to Winning Hackathons</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2019/06/a-hackers-guide-to-winning-hackathons/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/posts/2019/06/a-hackers-guide-to-winning-hackathons/</guid>
      <description>Hackathons are exhilarating. Nothing can eclipse the sheer adrenaline pump of building something in 24–36 hours. I was a visiting student at UC Berkeley for the Spring’19 semester. Berkeley is really close to the Silicon Valley and that gave me an amazing opportunity to take part in and win these 3 amazing hackathons:
  LA Hacks ’19 hosted by UCLA
  San Francisco DeveloperWeek Hackathon ’19 (America’s largest challenge-driven hackathon)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I will be a Computer Science graduate student at NYU Courant starting January 2021! Previously, I had the good fortune of working with Dr.Brandie Nonnecke at UC Berkeley at the intersection of machine learning and social network analysis where our work was presented to senators in Washington D.C. In the past, I have spent time as a research intern at Nvidia and CNeRG, IIT Kharagpur.
If you&#39;re starting your journey in machine learning, check out this roadmap I maintain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>E-mail : niladri@nyu.edu | niladrishekhardutt@gmail.com
GitHub : niladridutt
Twitter : @dutt_niladri
LinkedIn : niladridutt
Schedule a 30 min meeting with me</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/experience/</guid>
      <description>Nvidia Corporation
Research Intern | Jan 2020 - Present
  Working on fairness in computer vision systems  
 CITRIS Policy Lab, UC Berkeley
Undergraduate researcher | Supervisor : Dr.Brandie Nonnecke | Feb 2019 - Present
  Using machine learning to find how political tweets propagate and inuence elections. Improved topic coherence by using topic modeling after clustering based on social network analysis Presented research to senators in Washington, D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heyyy Ruu!</title>
      <link>https://niladridutt.com/ruuuu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://niladridutt.com/ruuuu/</guid>
      <description>OMG Ruu it&#39;s been 365 1/4 days! Time flies and yet it feels like I have known you for so long that I cannot imagine myself without you.
Seeeeee how cute we look together XD (probably our second date)  We&#39;ve come a long way since though but tui still khub choto and will always be. Lil baby Ruu &amp;lt;3  Bangalore was so much fun kid and I can&#39;t wait to live with you.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>